Guide to Rice University Commission on Women Records, 1985-2003 bulk 1985-1998 UA 061
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Commission on Women
1985-2003
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University. Office of the President
UA 061
4 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
The records reflect the activities of the Rice University Commission on Women (RUCOW). The collection spans almost 20 years and consists of materials associated with the Commission's work including task force reports that summarize the state of women's affairs at Rice (benefits, salary, promotion, child care, campus climate and visibility), surveys, memoranda, campus controversies, internal correspondence, and a collection of scholarly articles concerned with women's issues in academia.
Historical Sketch
In 1987, Rice president George Rupp formed a Commission on Women to investigate matters related to working women at Rice. Following an election, he appointed sixteen women from the faculty and staff to serve on the commission, which accepted the following charge: "The Commission will explore and evaluate issues relating to Rice women, especially in areas where inequities may exist, formulate specific recommendations to the Administration based upon its analysis, and educate the Rice community about behaviors and attitudes that operate to the detriment of women. The ultimate goal of the Commission will be to ensure a positive environment for women on campus."
The Commission, chaired by Professor Hally Beth Poindexter, set up task forces to study campus visibility, salaries, hiring practices, promotion and employee review practices, campus climate, benefits, and policies related to part-time employment. Over a hundred volunteers, both women and men, worked on the task forces, which met as often as weekly. However, before the task forces went into action the Commission felt it needed to address an immediate issue, the summer working conditions of college maintenance employees; an ad hoc subcommittee was formed in August 1987 and its report was issued September 1987.
The report of the Commission on Women 1987-88 consists of a summary report plus the reports of the seven task forces. The Commission also made recommendations, organized according to the individuals or departments responsible, so that each administrator can see the recommendations from the various task forces that would apply to his or her office or function.
In April and May 1989, Commission members met with three deans and the provost to discuss and take notes on the latters' "ideas for the future role of the Women's Commission, issues that needed clarification, and future problems that they could anticipate." In the spring of 1990 the Commission sent a memo to vice presidents and deans summarizing the Commission's five themes deemed to be of utmost importance of women on the Rice Campus and asking the VP's and Deans to identify "both general and specific points of progress and programs that have addressed these deficiencies, " which they did, some at length.
In September 1990, some of the original Commission members stayed on and others phased out, to allow for a mix of new blood and continuity of experience.
The Commission continued for several years thereafter. In the early 1990s, the Commission analyzed issues as child care needs for employees and students, and suggested creating an on-campus facility. During the mid-1990s under President Malcolm Gillis' direction, the Commission revisited the original 1988 report to determine whether recommendations and concerns were addressed by Rice University since that time.
Recently, President David W. Leebron established a new advisory group that will counsel the president and provost on issues facing women faculty. Based on the findings of a 2003 report of the Ad Hoc Advisory Committee, the report indicated a favorable campus-wide climate, however women faculty expressed lower degrees of satisfaction than men on most measures. The 2003 report is included in the collection.
General note
Historical sketch prepared by Nancy Boothe, and updated by Anthony Potoczniak. More recent information from the Rice News (vol. 14, no. 32, April 28, 2005)
Scope and Contents
Rice University Commission on Women (RUCOW) records consist of minutes of meetings, correspondence and memoranda, surveys, task force and commission reports, ballots, realia and memorabilia.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
These records have been placed with the Woodson Research Center by Kathleen Minadeo Johnson and Mildred Crocker in May, 2002. Additional materials on the Women's Commission dating from the 1990s were donated by Pat Kambhu in January, 2005.
Index Terms
Subjects
Women; Universities and colleges
Document Types
photographs; minutes (administrative records); corrrespondence
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University. Commission on Women
- Series I: Commission work (Meeting materials, agendas, minutes, ballots, reports), 1987-1998, 113645
  - Meetings (August, 1987 - September, 1990), 113663 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological files, Meetings minutes, correspondence, flyers, etc. (1987 - 1990), 113662 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronological files, Meetings minutes, correspondence, flyers, etc. (1990 - 1998), 113661 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dean's meeting notes (April, 1989 - July, 1990), 113660 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subcommittee on college maintenance employees, 1997, 113659 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Volunteer meeting minutes (October, 1997 - January, 1998), 113658 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - RUCOW History and mission statement (n.d), 113657 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Demographic analysis of majors of Rice juniors and seniors (1968-1969; 1997), 113656 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Schlumberger initiative for women (c.1996), 113655 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - RUCOW Ballots, 1990-1991, 113654 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - RUCOW Final summary report 1987-1988, 113653 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - RUCOW Report on Task Force on Campus Climate, 1988, 113652 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Possible appendices to Report on Campus Climate, 1988, 113651 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Draft reports to President Gillis (c.1998), 113650 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - RUCOW Report of the Commission on Women (1997-1998), 113649 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Appendices to Report of the Commission on Women (1997-1998) [1/2], 113648 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Appendices to Report of the Commission on Women (1997-1998) [2/2], 113647 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - RUCOW Report on child care services at Rice University (May, 1994), 113646 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series II: Task forces (Meeting materials, minutes, reports, statistics, etc.), 1987-1997, 113633
  - Establishment of task forces, lists, 113644 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Task force on benefits, 113643 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Task force on campus climate, includes report on Academic Climate Survey, Technical Report, June, 2003, 113642 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Task force on campus visibility [1/2], 113641 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Task force on campus visibility [1/2], 113640 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Task force on campus visibility, 1994 update, 113639 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Task force on hiring practices, 113638 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Task force on part-time employment, 113637 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Task force on promotions and employee review practices, 113636 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Task force on salaries, 113635 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Education benefits, 113634 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series III: Print ephemera (Newspaper clippings, journal articles, brochures, etc.), 1985-1997, 113600
  - Subseries A: Rice publications, 113631
    - Rice publications, Thresher, Rice News, Hooter (1985-1998), 113632 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Subseries B: Non-Rice publications, 113601
    - Scholarly articles and studies, Non-Rice (c.1989-1997), [1/3], 113621 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Academic outcomes of sexual harassment and assault, 1997, 113630
      - Ambient sexual harassment, 1997, 113629
      - The classroom climate: a chilly one of women? 1984, 113628
      - Antecedents and consequences of sexual harassment, n.d., 113627
      - The campus climate revisited: chilly for women faculty, administrators and graduate students, n.d., 113626
      - Classroom strategies for female faculty, 1995, 113625
      - Electronics and the dim view of the university, 1995, 113624
      - Evaluating the effectiveness of sexual harassment training, 1997, 113623
      - Job evaluation and gender, 1989, 113622
    - Scholarly articles and studies, Non-Rice (c.1989-1997), [2/3], 113614 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Job-related and psychological effects of sexual harassment in the workplace, 1997, 113620
      - Organizational influences on sexual harassment, 1996, 113619
      - Peer harassment: hassles for women on campus, n.d., 113618
      - Examinations and class practices, 1996, 113617
      - Seeing and evaluating people, n.d., 113616
      - Sexual harassment and assault in academia, 1995, 113615
    - Scholarly articles and studies, Non-Rice (c.1989-1997), [3/3], 113607 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Structural equation models of sexual harassment, 113613
      - Title IX, 113612
      - Tolerance for sexual harassment, 1997, 113611
      - "Too strong for a woman": the five words that created Title IX, 113610
      - Where do we go from here, 113609
      - Women faculty at work in the classroom, or, why it hurts to be a woman in labor, 113608
    - Scholarly article: "The Chilly Classroom Climate: A Guide to Improve the Education of Women," 1996, 113606 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Women (Faculty) in the Classroom, 113605 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Women's Research Network News (1994-1995); NAWE Conference Material, 1994, 113604 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - AACU: On Campus With Women (Spring 1994 - Fall, 1997), 113603 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Center for Women Policy Studies, publications and brochures, (c.1996), 113602 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Ephemera (Buttons, poster, banner, print negatives) (c. 1987), 113596
  - RUCOW banner and poster, 1987, 113599 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - RUCOW buttons, 113598 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Negatives from RUCOW open house, n.d., 113597 (Box 4, Folder 6)